Autoimmune hepatitis
Email this page to a friend Print Facebook X Pinterest
Autoimmune hepatitis causes inflammation of the liver. It occurs when immune cells mistake the liver's normal cells for harmful invaders and attack them.

Causes
This form of hepatitis is an autoimmune disease. The body's immune system cannot tell the difference between healthy body tissue and harmful, outside substances. The result is an immune response that destroys normal body tissues.

Liver inflammation, or hepatitis, may occur along with other autoimmune diseases. These include:

Graves disease
Inflammatory bowel disease
Rheumatoid arthritis
Scleroderma
Sjögren syndrome
Systemic lupus erythematosus
Thyroiditis
Type 1 diabetes
Ulcerative colitis
Autoimmune hepatitis may occur in family members of people with autoimmune diseases. There may be a genetic cause.

This disease is most common in girls and women.

Symptoms
Symptoms may include:

Fatigue
General discomfort, uneasiness, or ill feeling (malaise)
Itching
Loss of appetite
Nausea or vomiting
Joint pain
Pale or clay-colored stools
Dark urine
Abdominal distention
Absence of menstruation (amenorrhea) may also be a symptom.

Exams and Tests
Tests for autoimmune hepatitis include the following blood tests:

Liver function tests.
Anti-liver kidney microsome type 1 antibody (anti LKM-1).
Anti-nuclear antibody (ANA).
Anti-smooth muscle antibody (SMA).
Serum IgG.
Liver biopsy to look for long-term hepatitis.
You may also have an ultrasound of your liver.
Treatment
You may need prednisone or other corticosteroid medicines to help reduce the inflammation. Azathioprine and 6-mercaptopurine are medicines used to treat other autoimmune disorders. They have also been shown to help people with autoimmune hepatitis. Other medicines are occasionally used. The goal of treatment is to put the disease into remission, and then keep it into remission.

Some people may need a liver transplant.

Outlook (Prognosis)
The outcome varies. Corticosteroid and other medicines may slow the progress of the disease. However, autoimmune hepatitis may advance to cirrhosis. This could require a liver transplant.

Possible Complications
Complications may include:

Cirrhosis
Side effects from steroids and other medicines
Hepatocellular carcinoma
Liver failure
Bleeding from varices
Ascites
Hepatic encephalopathy
When to Contact a Medical Professional
Contact your health care provider if you notice symptoms of autoimmune hepatitis.

Prevention
In most cases, autoimmune hepatitis cannot be prevented. Knowing the risk factors may help you detect and treat the disease early.

Alternative Names
Lupoid hepatitis; Chronic active hepatitis

References
Czaja AJ. Autoimmune hepatitis. In: Feldman M, Friedman LS, Brandt LJ, eds. Sleisenger and Fordtran's Gastrointestinal and Liver Disease. 11th ed. Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier; 2021:chap 90.

Pawlotsky J-M. Chronic viral and autoimmune hepatitis. In: Goldman L, Cooney KA, eds. Goldman-Cecil Medicine. 27th ed. Philadelphia, PA: Elsevier; 2024:chap 135.

